Thorsten,
Yes, overriding initSelf() is usually the way to add your customized fields to a widget.
In this case however you need access to one of the fields that are already created for this widget - that is the select box containing the different moderation states. Unfortunately this member in OModerationStateSelectSearchWidget is private, so there really is no good way of getting hold of the select box, manipulating it to contain the Non Public Pending state as it's own entry (rather than as lumped together with the Public Pending state). 
This leaves you with two options, as I see it: either you could writer your very own widget that does pretty much the same thing as theOModerationStateSelectSearchWidget. Or you could add another search widget to the stack of search widgets: this new search widget could have a checkbox saying something like "For pending posts, only include non public posts". The search widget would implement the buildQuery method, which allows it to add clauses to the Lucene query that will be posed to the index, and, provided that the checkbox is checked, add a clause to the query that requires that search hits are in Non Public Pending state.
I admit this is not a very neat solution, but I think it's the best option right now. We